hey friend in this video i'm bringing
you the complete beginner's guide to
watercolor
this is basically the in person
watercolor workshop that i taught for
over eight years so i'm covering
everything from the supplies i use and
why
color theory basic shapes and strokes
brush techniques
compound strokes and leaves and then
we're bringing it all together for a
full
floral wreath where i'm talking about
composition and color theory and
everything that we covered in this huge
video now just as an fyi this is the big
video so we have all of the chapters
segmented out for you in the big video
but we're gonna break off each
individual chapter to be its own
individual video so if you want for
quick reference you can check out my
watercolor basics playlist
to go back to each individual chapter if
you want for quick reference now
we have a ton to cover so let's dive in
okay let's talk about supplies
the supplies that i use are all high
quality but budget friendly at the same
time for the most part
and so i want to talk a little bit more
in detail about the supplies i use why i
use them
so let's first let's talk about my
palette
this is a traveler's plastic watercolor
palette i use this
for filming i use this for traveling
i've had this palette for
probably about six or seven years
whoopsie we've got a little
i don't know where that came from uh
i've had this palette for about six or
seven years i love it i also have a
ceramic palette by
sylvan clay works that i absolutely love
but that thing stays on my desk because
it's pretty heavy
um and i use about i think
uh 14 of these colors now because i
added a couple more this past year um so
if you're looking at my palette and
you're like wait that looks like
way more colors than just 14 colors
that's because i have
this pink in here i i used for about a
week seven years ago and i haven't used
it since and then same thing with these
two gr or
these two greens i rarely ever use this
is windsor green this is olive green
and i don't use these this one um i
thought it said the tube said watercolor
but it was actually gouache
and so it's hard as a rock in here um
and i don't use it i could obviously
scoop it out scrape it out but i
have been lazy before i move on to the
pigments that i use the colors and their
names
um one thing that i do get asked about
this palette is what this thing is for
and that is if you're standing and
painting you can hold your palette with
your thumb
inside here and then you have little
brush holders right here but i never
stand in paint if you do stand in paint
though
that's pretty fun and then it folds up
and can travel
with you it's perfect for little art
retreats or something like that if
you're traveling and painting
all right so let's talk about the colors
that i actually do use
in my palette starting at the top with
mars black
i stick with all of my cool colors
on the left side and then all of my warm
colors on the right side
so if you're new to this channel i talk
about separating warm and cool colors
quite often we'll get more into it in
the color theory video
of why i separate my cool versus warm
colors and which ones make up cool and
warm
but simply if i am mixing let's say
orange and blue for example in the same
mixing dish or mixing well area it's
just going to make muddy brown
colors so contrasting colors are gonna
make brown
and so i have all of my cool colors on
the left side all of my warm colors on
the right side so
black um this is a cool black it's mars
black by windsor newton all of my colors
are bray
windsor newton and they are professional
level so
if you are going to all the links we
have in this video
and you're looking up the paints and you
want to buy or want to purchase
the paints that i use you might be
startled by some of the price tags
however i always use if you're buying a
14 milliliter tube of paint of
watercolor paint
you're using about a quarter or a third
of that tube
to squirt the technical term
squirt um a dish worth of paint in here
and i let my pigment dry overnight so
for about 24 hours and then i use it i
just wet the area
wet the pigment that i want soak up the
pigment that i want
etc and then go to my paper there's a
couple reasons for this
so instead of using paint straight from
the tube like a lot of people do which
is totally fine
um i like to let it dry first because
it's just like watercolor pans or cakes
of
pigment you can still get some really
rich opaque pigment
if you you know work your brush in there
a lot but the
number one reason why i do it this way
is to not waste pigment
if you are going straight from the tube
you know with wet pigment a lot of
people will
waste the pigment and then along with
that it lasts
a really long time so like i haven't
refilled eye paint every single day
and i haven't refilled my my pigments in
about three or four months i'm getting
low on some of my yellows these are the
same yellows by the way i'll talk about
it in a second
so i'm getting low and i'll just squirt
a little bit more of the wet pigment and
on top of it
but so a 14 milliliter tube might cost
you 15 16
but it's gonna last you eight to twelve
months most likely
if you're if you're painting every
single day obviously certain colors will
run out quicker i run out quicker of the
yellow
a lot uh quicker than let's say cobalt
blue because i rarely use cobalt blue
it's only for special occasions
um so you know look at that when you're
looking at the price tag up front
and then maybe just start with a few
colors or start with just primary colors
in black or something
to get you started and see what you see
the difference between high quality
paint and
student level or something that is not
as quality
so mars black windsor newton
professional level this is burnt umber
um then we have ultramarine violet then
i have
prussian blue i've got cobalt blue
phthalo turquoise again this was this
weird turquoise gouache that i
thought was watercolor this is winter
windsor green
blue shade that i haven't used in a few
years
i just add blue to my sap green which is
the green that i use
all the time i use this every single day
if i'm painting florals this is my
favorite green
and then olive green i again i don't
really use it that much because i'll
usually if i want like an olivey
green color i'll just add burnt umber to
sap green so
these two colors you really don't need
unless you don't want to keep mixing up
the
the blue greens and the brownish sagey
greens then
maybe just i mean you can buy them if
you want otherwise i just mix
up secondary colors with sap green
and then i have two dishes of lemon
yellow deep
on my cool color side because i like to
mix up greens with sap green
and then i also like to mix up greens
with my turquoisey colors
and so if i used the same yellow
obviously you can see
by my palette i'm very very type b and
so
i am going directly on top of dishes of
color with other colors
on my brush if that stresses you out
then you can just go into your mixing
wells but the reason why i do this is
because it's quicker it's faster it
allows me to
work wet and wet a lot quicker and i can
always just add water to this and dab it
up
clean it up with a paper towel if i need
to then over here i have cobalt
turquoise and manganese blue
this manganese blue and cobalt turquoise
i recently added i'm not a huge fan of
the cobalt turquoise because i was
looking for something that was like
macaw feather blue turquoise the actual
element turquoise so
manganese blue is like a new addition to
my palette as of
a few months ago and i'm loving it great
color and then over here on the warm
side
we have scarlet lake this is like an
orangey tinted
red so i'm not using cadmium red or
you know colors that are your
traditional reds or traditional blues i
like to have that kind of like
off what's the word not
hipster colors trendy colors
corally red you know it's cute um and
then
opera rose this is a bright neon pink
color when you get it by itself in a lot
of pigment on your brush it's beautiful
i don't remember which orange this was
but again this is one of the colors
that's been in my palette for about
seven years and i never use it
i think it's windsor orange i don't even
know if that's color anymore i haven't
said that in like
years so i don't remember cadmium orange
i rarely use just because it has cadmium
in it
but it is a great orange if you want to
mix up oranges i
usually do some scarlet lake and yellow
or opera rose and yellow for a bit more
of a blushy orange
but cadmium orange is a great orange it
just
is it has a toxic ingredient in it
unfortunately
again never use this color don't
remember what it is i think it's also
gouache because it's super duper hard
um but never use it and then this is
lemon yellow deep lemon yellow deep
and yellow ochre so i use like i do
lemon yellow deep over here
two different um oranges or what i'm
mixing up these are like for my muted
oranges with
yellow ochre or um you know
not as vibrant and then over here i'm
mixing scarlet lake or
uh aqua rose with it so all of these
colors are by windsor newton they're all
professional level
again everybody is going to be different
every artist is different
some artists have really great success
with student level paints
however i use professional level paints
just because i love the rich pigments
they are
pure pigments there's less binding agent
in the tube of paint so
student level paints are less expensive
because they're using a lot more binding
agents to
um basically lessen the intensity of the
pigment but also bind it to
the other mixture and the other
ingredients in the mixture of the tube
to make it cheaper so they're not like
using pure pigment um and there's you
know more binding agent in there so it's
not as rich it doesn't blend as well
i've noticed obviously there's a lot of
people out there though that use student
level have great success so
start where you can with the budget that
you have i love professional level
though just because of
all of the capabilities i have with it
the rich pigment like i said
so there is my palette now let's talk
about brushes
so for brushes
for my brushes um i really only use
these three brushes
except for if i'm painting like a
stripes pattern
or something that you know is a big wash
i will use a wash brush by the same
brand
or a flat brush by the same brand but my
absolute favorite three brushes are
these three
round tip brushes by princeton these
princeton brushes are from the series
heritage 4050
and i used the size 2 size 6
in size 16 round brushes most frequently
um the size 6 being my all-time favorite
brush if i was stranded on a desert
island
what what would be one supply one art
supply like out of everything that i
would take
with me it would be this brush which i
guess i couldn't use it if i didn't have
paper so that's unfortunate
but this would be the brush that i would
take i love this brush it's very
versatile all these brushes
are synthetic sable hair brushes so
no harming of animals very very high
quality brushes
they princeton i've been to a couple of
in person like i went to a trade show
with them back in 2018
in las vegas and i got to meet the
founder howard who is like
literally the sweetest man of all time
we got along so well i love him so much
the whole team at princeton is amazing
um but i got to hear him talk about the
making of these brushes and how
um they've been handed down this
japanese style of making these brushes
with the ferrule and the
the hair and the binding from a third
generation
brush maker in japan and all of this
fascinating
stuff and why they use these or why they
created the technology for these brushes
and
no harming of any weasels and what you
know the actual natural hair brushes
which no
shame on anybody who does that but i
just prefer not to and
they're at like an a quarter of the
price of a natural brush
with i believe better technology than
natural brushes now i know i'm gonna get
hate in the comments from the natural
brush
fanatics um actual sable brush fanatics
because people are
very very uh pearl clutchy
when it comes to their brushes their
natural hair brushes and i totally get
it
but these synthetic sable hair brushes
from princeton
are incredibly flexible they snap right
back to form when they're really wet and
you maybe push on it with a vertical
hold like this and the brush fans out
they snap right back to their fine point
tip
so they're really flexible really snappy
they also hold
a lot of pigment and water which is a
huge advantage when you're painting with
watercolor
obviously acrylic oil all of the
different mediums are going to have
different technology
and advantages with the type of hair
that they use the feral
all of that kind of stuff so you
definitely want to check out the
different
series of brushes that princeton has if
you're painting with acrylic and not
watercolor obviously because it's going
to be different but all these brushes
are really snappy flexible and that was
a huge
uh like eye-opening thing for me when i
first started painting with watercolor i
didn't have these brushes
and about a year into painting with
watercolor i discovered princeton
and i was like oh this is what painting
with good brushes feels like so
make sure you check out those brushes
all linked below i use again
size 2 6 and 16 the size 16 is for my
big flowers
big peony petals big leaves big or if i
want to cover a large wash
area and i don't have a wash brush with
me then i'll use this size 16.
um and then size 6 is pretty much what i
use 80
of the time when i'm painting florals
and then for small details
i'll use a size 2. i love using this
size 2 brush too if i'm painting
something like architectural drawings
or style paintings with fine details or
portraits where i'm getting really
really fine details as well so these are
great versatile brushes you really don't
need much more than this
obviously i have jars and jars of
brushes that i've just accumulated over
the years i think that's just like an
artist thing to do we love collecting
brushes and we think we're going to use
them all the time
i use them very infrequently
unfortunately and
have been gifted to many many friends
over the years and many
kids who are starting to pick up
watercolor so that's a good use for them
but
these three i always come back to love
them tons
all right next let's talk about paper
paper i use legion paper stonehenge aqua
cold press so the biggest question
people have when it comes to what paper
should i use for watercolor is
should i use cold press or should i use
hot press and there are many
talented professional artists who use
hot press there's many talented
professional watercolors to use cold
press like myself and the main reason
why i use cold press
is because of the texture so hot pressed
paper
the actual process of making the paper
is going to use a hot press
that basically smooths out all of the
pulp all of the texture
in the cotton paper so this is 100
cotton paper
and it smooths it out in the process of
making the paper cold press
doesn't use that process obviously it's
a cold press so it's going to have
this nice toothy texture to it's got if
you zoom in really closely
which you don't zoom in with your
eyeballs that's just with cameras i
guess
but if you look really closely at your
paper and you have cold pressed paper
you should see some bumps um in texture
that toothy texture is what helps
hold the water and the pigment in place
while it's drying
so i tried using hot press paper and i
just i
maybe it's my style maybe it's just the
way that i paint but i do
use a lot of water when i'm painting and
so with hot pressed paper i kept
noticing that i would have to come back
to
areas or petals when i was over painting
something else to
like mess with it and make sure that no
hard lines were you know happening
on the paper because a lot of movement
happens on really smooth paper a lot of
hard lines happen with on really smooth
paper because it's not being absorbed by
that toothy texture
so i prefer cold pressed paper um
just because of that but you want to
make sure when you're using paper you
want to make sure that you
are using 100 cotton paper
it's acid free and then i use a 140
pound or 300 gsm
paper i don't really go any uh
much above that so i don't use 300 pound
paper
um mainly because i found that it
absorbs
perfectly with 140 pound paper and then
this
is a block of paper instead of a pad
so pads are glued just at the top or
just on one side
of the paper so let's say you have 15
sheets they're just glued
at the top edge or one of the edges a
block of paper
you usually are glued on all four sides
and there's either
a corner that's left unglued or for the
legion paper it's on the side right here
like about an inch and a half is unglued
so that is where you would slide your
finger or a soft ruler or a canvas bone
to lift off the top sheet and the reason
why i paint with a block of paper is
because it keeps my
it keeps all edges of my paper
completely flat while i'm painting
because we're painting with watercolor
we're adding water to paper
and that's going to create buckles
that's going to create warps and divots
and dips and valleys in our paper
and so if you're painting with just a
loose sheet on your table and you're
noticing that it's like creating this v
with your
water and pigment pooling into that v
because it's creating a valley because
you're adding water to your paper
then you're gonna get some funky drying
moments you're gonna get some hard lines
and some wonky things that you don't
want so
i use a block for that reason if i do
use just a single sheet of paper then i
will
pull out my 3m artist tape that blue
painters tape
and tape all four sides down on a piece
of cardboard
instead of taping it on my table because
i like to rotate my paper
when i'm painting so if you do work with
loose sheets or you have a pad of paper
and you don't want that to happen then
just take off that top sheet from your
pad
or your loose sheet and tape it to
something that you can rotate
um you can even use if you you know just
have like a used block or a used pad you
can tape it to
this but that way you can still rotate
your paper
so that is paper another great band of
brand of paper is arch
arch arches so many different ways you
can say it i'm not fancy
so we're saying arches but arches is
great paper it's just slightly more
expensive than this legion paper
and i find that this in fabriano is an
excellent paper
as well still more expensive than legion
so legion was my go-to
after working on arches working on
fabriano for a while
a few years because i found that it was
a great uh
it was very similar to fabriano um
texture wise and also the off whiteness
it's not too bright white
so i went with this paper because it's
cheaper and because i'm recommending
supplies all the time i didn't want to
recommend you know 40
pad of paper like arches is so there you
go
and then one more thing that i always
have on hand is paper towels or
a washcloth or something i can wash or
dry my brushes off and get rid of
pigment onto
and then i use two cups of water one cup
is for
you can rinse off cool colors and the
other cup is for rinsing off warm colors
or you can use it for your dirty cup of
water where you're rinsing off your
brush
if you have pigment still left on it and
then clean cup of water
to pick up clean cup clean water before
you go to your pigment or your paper
so so we have a supply playlist
all dedicated to my love of supplies
many videos in there
if you want to learn more about supplies
that i use and why i use them check out
that playlist we'll link it in this
video
okay so color theory wow this is old
you see that oh wow okay so color theory
i used to teach
these in-person watercolor classes ever
since
what year do you think i started 2014
yeah
probably 2014. so in 2014 i started
teaching in-person
watercolor workshops and calligraphy
workshops but we're talking about
watercolor
today and i would bring along as a part
of the watercolor kits for each student
i would bring along these booklets i had
them printed
and they were basically you know they
covered supplies they covered color
theory
and all of the things that you need to
know to get started with watercolor
and um we are going to link to this
ebook so you can print it out at home if
you want to but
there is going to be a good section in
here if you don't have my book everyday
watercolor which goes way more in depth
on color theory
than this booklet does but if you don't
have it and you want some
you know reference you want some guide
to help you along
through this video then i definitely
recommend
downloading that freebie that we have
it's free all you have to do is enter
your name and email and it will be sent
to you so you can download it and print
it at home if you want to
but let's talk about color theory
because that is something that
most beginners and even if you've been
painting for a while
most people kind of don't explore enough
um obviously we know basics of color
theory for the most part or
most people do i think because it's just
kind of taught in elementary or high
school art class
um but it's always a reference point
it's something that
i am very grateful that i've taken the
time to study more
um and just as from my experience
in learning piano over the years when i
i started learning piano when i was 12
and i started with a teacher that taught
me how to sight read and that's very
valuable obviously being able to sight
read but then i switched piano teachers
and he taught me
music theory so he taught me the
foundations of why certain chords work
together and how they harmonize
and thirds and fifths and tonics and
subdominant and all these different
things about music theory so that i
could just sit at a piano
and play because i understood
relationships between
chords within a single key and this is
the same thing so color
theory is going to teach you color
relationships how they correspond with
each other
so that when you are looking at a blank
sheet of paper
you can pick up your brush and you can
have more confidence of where to put
certain colors you know how to blend
how to mix colors a little bit more
confidently and easily because you
understand color theory so
exploring color theory this is like i
mean like you could teach a thousand
hours on color
color theory in the color wheel and
color relationships and we're not going
to do that obviously
because that would be very boring
eventually um but
i'm going to briefly talk about it in
this video so that you you can actually
i think it's just so eye-opening and i
think it's very
um fun to talk about so obviously a
color wheel consists of
at least three colors those three colors
being that always are on this color
on a color wheel are red blue and yellow
your primary colors
so this is traditional color theory i'm
not going to get in the more you know
the battles between the different types
of color theory i'm going with
traditional color theory because that's
how i was taught
but red blue and yellow sit as a triad
or triangle away from each other on the
color wheel at all times
different color wheels will have you
know red blue or yellow at the top this
one has red at the top then we've got
blue over here and yellow is sitting
over here so they always make a triangle
depending on you know what type of color
wheel you have
this is a tertiary color wheel so we
have 12 colors
i mixed up more than 12 but this is a
tertiary color wheel will have 12 colors
or 12 little pie slices
and so we've got red blue and yellow
your three primary colors these are the
colors that you can't mix up
um you know just out of the blue without
any other
colors these colors mixed together will
make
brown or black sometimes depending on
what type of red what type of blue what
type of yellow you use
but usually we'll make black so if you
don't have black in your palette or you
ran out or something just try mixing up
your three primary colors
but combined together in equal parts
two primary colors combined together in
equal parts will make what's called a
secondary color
so secondary colors are equal parts to
primary colors
so red and blue and equal parts parts
makes violet or purple
blue and yellow and equal parts makes
green yellow and red in equal parts
makes orange and then we're getting more
and more
into the family unit of this color wheel
with
tertiary colors tertiary colors are the
ones with the hyphen
in the name so red orange yellow orange
yellow green blue green
blue violet red violet and by the name
the secondary
name in the title of the of the color is
going to be
what it's leaning more towards or
sometimes it's the first name so yellow
orange obviously there's more
yellow in the mixture than there is red
um
yellow green there's more yellow in the
mixture than there is blue etc
all right very basic but let's actually
get into the relationships and why this
matters
so um there's a bunch of different types
of
color combinations when you're just
looking at a color wheel you can combine
obviously we can talk about contrasting
colors those colors always sit directly
opposite of each other on the color
wheel and i want to talk about it in
terms of because i'm such a visual
person and this is just how my piano
teacher taught me when he was teaching
me chords and shapes of chords and how
they relate to each other i'm just a
visual person
so if you think about opposites let's
talk about it in our actual human
interactions in relationships
you hear that all the time opposites
attract so contrasting colors can also
be
complementary colors but it's when
they're used properly or when they
um one is maybe a lighter hue than the
other so
one can shine and that other contrast or
element of the contrast is a little bit
more of a supportive role
um or maybe this isn't a direct contrast
obviously but maybe instead of having
red and green
you know traditional totally so instead
of having just
red pure red and pure green maybe you
shift the green a little bit to the left
or to the right and you add a little
blue to it or you add a little bit of
yellow to it
to offset that direct contrast so when
this comes to
using contrasting colors or
complementary colors in your paintings
you want to keep an eye on areas where
you can add contrast because
contrast brightens the colors on your
paper
contrast adds a bit of whoa what's that
it makes people want to look at it
and maybe stay there for a little bit
longer but if it's used improperly
if it's creating a lot of disharmony
then people are going to want to look
away they don't really know why it's a
subconscious
decision and it's usually because you're
using
something that just causes more strain
than people want to look at so
that will typically happen if for
example you're using
equal dominance of value so a really
deep
rich powerful red and a really deep rich
powerful green
if that's used a lot or if it's used to
improperly like if you're painting with
a really light
floral piece let's say and then you have
a really bright or bold red next to a
really bold green
then people are gonna just land right
there and stay right there and they're
not gonna move across your paper so you
wanna make sure that you're using
contrasting slash complementary colors
uh properly so that they create harmony
however there are really interesting
ways that you can use
bold contrasting like what you would
think would be
you know grinding on each other colors
red and green or blue and orange purple
and yellow etc
um on purpose and it makes the piece
really interesting so
if i'm using that bold blue or bold red
and green i'm just making sure to create
balance on my paper
in terms of how the actual paper feels
weighted so if i just have the
bold red and green up in this corner
that balance it's going to be tipping to
the left corner and it's going to feel
like the paper is falling off and people
are just going to land and stay right
there and that's
we don't want that but if we're creating
purpose with our balance and we're
creating
even weighted zigzag across our paper
like this or an s curve across our paper
our paper is going to feel like it's
it's balanced it's even it's not tipping
on one side or the other literally
feels that way or looks that way with
your eyes i know this may
sound weird but i'm just a very visual
person and it's the same thing with
photography it's the same thing
with creating balance and composition
when you're painting you want to make
sure
your painting isn't feeling like it's
tipping over
so we've got red and green um our
contrasting colors anything that's
directly opposite of each other on the
color wheel is going to be contrasting
or complementary colors because they are
literally the most unlike each other
they're furthest away from each other on
the color wheel um
direct opposites of each other so um
that would be a contrasting color
palette combination
one of my favorite color palette
combinations when i'm trying to create a
really subtle change or a really subtle
movement with people's eyes when they're
looking at a piece of paper or a
composition
is an analogous color palette so an
analogous color palette
basically uses three or four or more
depends on
you know the amount of colors you use
hues that
sit right next to each other on the
color wheel so we could do red orange
orange yellow orange and yellow
this is going to be the most subtle
transition with people's eyes
might sound basic but think about it if
people are subtly transitioning or
moving to green instead of just jumping
from red orange to green
it's going to be a lot more easy for
their eyes to move through these colors
than jumping
so it's the same thing with you know
using secondary and tertiary colors are
going to help bridge that gap between
your contrasting colors
so again if we are using a red and green
element up here let's say
i'm making sure to mix in some red
orange some orange and yellows
around it so that it's subtly
transferring between red and green
instead of just
boom there's your red and green if
that's my purpose there
so analogous color palette is when
you're using hues that sit directly next
to each other on the color wheel
their neighbors their family members
they know each other quite well
because they're very similar in hue and
they help people's eyes move really
subtly really peacefully through your
piece
which is lovely so secondary and
tertiary colors are really key
in bridging that gap because primary
colors are always going to be
you know far further not obviously
as far as contrasting colors but they're
going to be further away from each other
um than any tertiary color would be so
those tertiary colors
come in handy when you're painting and a
lot of people
especially beginners kind of just mix up
their colors quickly without intention
and so
think about how you could add a tertiary
color on a p
on let's just say a leaf where you have
a lot of
blue green and yellow green maybe adding
in some or where you have a lot of just
green secondary green maybe adding in
some blue green and yellow green will
help mix it up and bring in a nice
peaceful
movement element to the to the branch
okay so that is
extremely basic color theory um there's
a lot more color combinations that you
can research on your own
um but i would recommend creating an
actual color wheel i have a tutorial
where i
teach you how to create this so i'll
link to it in this video if you want to
paint one of your own and set it up in
your office or wherever you paint
as a reference and a guide that you can
always
look back on but next that's kind of
related to color theory i want to talk
about
warm colors and cool colors and value
scales so
if we look at a color wheel we're going
to separate
our color wheel based on warm colors and
cool colors so
anything that's from yellow and red
violet
up so this half of the color wheel is
going to be
warm colors so anything that has like a
base or
a base hue of red is going to be warm
colors think
fire and then we've got our cool colors
underneath here this half of the color
wheel is going to be
cool colors so anything that's the base
of water um or
you know that feeling of water is going
to be a cool color so blue greens yellow
greens
violet red violet i would consider a
warm color
just because it has that element of fire
poking through or that reddish hue
poking through
there are we're not going to get into
the nitty-gritty but
there are blues that can be warm
undertones there are
reds that can be cool undertones but
basically speaking
red and cool colors are going to be
separate halves of the color wheel
what did i just say warm and cool colors
are going to be separate halves of the
color wheel
and the reason why i i point this out is
because
if you're painting with two cups of
water um a lot of people get confused on
where to rinse off their warm colors
where to rinse off their cool colors
that's the
the process that i use for cleaning my
brushes off so if you do the same then
you know anything over here is going to
be in your warm cup and then anything
that
is a cool color is going to be in your
other cup
and the reason for that is you're always
going to have with warm and cool colors
you're always going to have
one warm color one cool color in a
contrasting uh
relationship so red and green for
example red is a warm color
green is a cool color and contrasting
colors whenever they're mixed together
always make a muddy murky color it can
be gray it can be brown
and that turns your water brown if
you're only using
one cup of water or you're mixing up
mixing off cool colors and warm colors
in the same cup then you're always going
to get muddy murky water
and the style of painting that i do i
like to have rich bold bright colors
pure colors
i like to keep my colors as clean as
possible when they're on my paper
and so if you like that as well then i
like to separate my cups of water so
that i rinse off warm colors in one and
cool colors in the other
so there is that and then let's talk
about value scales so
a color isn't just by itself
um one shade or one value
uh there are so many with this is why i
love watercolor so much we don't need to
use white paint to
to lighten the color we're going to use
water to make it more transparent
and we don't need to you know multiple
tubes of paint to make these different
shades or values so a value is the
lightness and darkness
of a color the hue is the actual color
itself
or the pigment um and so right here this
value scale is scarlett lake
um and i started with you know a rich
amount of scarlet like on my brush i'll
just show you
so to do a value scale i'm going to grab
my size 16 brush
and a lot of scarlet lake
so that i can show this pigment in its
darkest value
so all of your all of your watercolors
that you use
you can get multiple values of that same
color by just using water so
right about here is where i'm swirling
my brush
and trying to pick up a lot of this
pigment so it's more opaque
or a darker version darker value of
scarlet like
then i'm just going to use a slanted
hold about 15 degrees away from my paper
with my size 16 brush and paint a little
swatch area here so there is
probably my darkest value of scarlet
lake
um using a lot more pigment than water
but then to lighten the color i'm just
going to lighten what i have on my brush
by flicking my brush and my water cup
back and forth a couple of times
like so and making sure to always swipe
off the excess water
on my jar and then we have a slightly
lighter value
so one thing to notice or take note of
when you are doing
trying to lighten a value maybe in the
middle of a painting you're
trying to get a lighter value of
something make sure you're not too
aggressive
with your flicking or not aggressive
enough so there's two different types of
people there's people that are really
aggressive and they
get rid of all that pigment in one foul
swoop and then there's people who are
really scared of the water
and do it very delicately so take note
of which person you are
but if you're just trying to gradually
lighten
the value of a color um i'm going back
and forth a few times
and always making sure i'm swiping the
brush off on the edge of my cup or
dabbing it on my paper towel
and we're just gradually getting lighter
and lighter and let's say
i wanted to get to scarlet lake's
lightest value
then i would basically just get rid of
all that pigment from my brush as much
as i can
and obviously swipe off the excess water
and we have basically water with just a
tint
of red or scarlet lake
so value scales are a really great way
to practice
just gradually lightening a cup
lightening
gradually lightening a color um it helps
you get used to the movement get used to
that muscle memory of
rinsing off your brush just gradually
over um
a gradual scale so i'd practice value
scales again i teach you how to do that
in this little booklet if you want to
download it for free it's in there and
then also about hue scales
if you want to mix up two hues together
you know creating secondary and tertiary
colors
obviously red by itself scarlet like by
itself is going to be
a primary color red and then
the more yellow pigment i roll around in
the more
orange or red orange it's going to get
and then eventually yellow
and if this stresses you out going
directly on top
of your pigment you can mix up the
colors in a secondary
well over here in your palette um but
this
again can be wiped up with some water
and a paper towel it can be cleaned up
so don't you worry
this is just a great way to practice
painting quickly
um because when you're in the middle of
a big painting like a floral piece let's
say
and you you're painting a big red peony
but you want another flower next to it
that's maybe a red orange
then you have red on your on your
paintbrush you can all you need to do is
just go to your yellow
and make it move it a little bit more
towards that red orange tertiary color
so hue scale value scales all
really really important stuff to
practice especially if you're a beginner
in getting used to color mixing getting
used to gradually lightening a color
with water because the more transparent
the color is the lighter it is going to
be the more pigment you have on your
brush the more opaque or darker it's
going to be
and then again studying color theory and
color relationships
because we're always wanting to create
harmony with our colors
and finding out where colors are maybe
creating an element
of unbalance or it feels like it's
tipping on our paper
composition wise i also have a color
chart
video so if you're one of the people who
really struggles with
knowing what colors to mix together to
make certain pigments or hues
um i have a color chart video which is
going to be
really fun for you it it's it's i think
one of the most
beautiful things to paint even though
it's just squares um
but it's going to teach you color mixing
it's going to teach you how to
uh find certain colors out of maybe
surprising combinations so
definitely check out that video all
right let's talk about
two watercolor techniques you must know
so the first thing that i'm going to
talk about is going to be wet
in wet painting so the two techniques
that you must know with watercolor are
wet and wet
and wet and dry wet and wet is literally
how it sounds
two areas of wet pigment or water touch
and blend and it it creates the magic
moment
this magic moment
um that's the magic with watercolor is
wet and wet painting it's the best
i love it but there is a time and place
for wet and dry i love wet and dry too
it's for more layers for adding you know
pigment on top of dried pigment so wet
pigment
pigment on top of dry pigment it's when
you're going to be able to create a lot
more depth a lot more detail and shading
uh is using wet and dry so there's a
time and place for wet and dry
especially if you're painting
realistic style florals or portraits or
whatever anything that's more realistic
you're going to use wet and dry quite a
lot but wet and wet
is you know you can use it for more
loose style florals you can use it for
blending and shading and creating layers
of depth first
with blending and shading before adding
the detail in a realistic
painting so wet and wet literally how it
sounds
wet and dry literally how it sounds but
let's talk about wet and wet first
because there's going to be three
different methods that you can use
to achieve wet and wet painting and this
is again
something that you really want to
practice and tackle as a beginning
watercolorist because
it's where the magic happens it's where
you're going to see those amazing blooms
or bleeds between
two colors or two hue values of
you know lighter or darker values so you
want to practice it for
sure so let's talk about the first
way to achieve wet and wet painting and
we are going to
talk about pulling so i'm going to grab
my size 16 brush and let's do
a prussian blue it doesn't matter if
you're if you're following along in this
video it doesn't matter what color
you're pulling up you just want to make
sure that you have a really dark
or opaque value of this first swatch
that we're going to do so i've got a lot
of water
on my brush so i can pick up a lot of
pigment
and
this prussian blue all i'm going to do
is literally just show you a demo of how
to do this pulling method so it's not
like a
has to be exactly like this but let's
just lay down
a nice swatch area
of this prussian blue so wet and wet
like i said
it's exactly how it sounds if your
this pigment right here is too dry
you're not going to be able to achieve
wet and wet so see how i can move this
pigment around
in like this little puddle area that's
going to be perfect for the pulling
method
but i also don't have a little bulb of
puddle
situation happening that would be too
much water so
to use the pulling method i'm going to
just grab water on my brush
it's okay if there's still a little
pigment on your brush and
i am going to swipe just that very
bottom edge of the blue
with water like so and then
pull it down so as you can see that
prussian blue is
bleeding as far as the further down i go
with my water the further down this
bleed is going to go
so that would be called pulling so you
can pull
pigments or areas of pigment or water
down with swiping and then working your
way down with water
or with a color you can do pulling
with colors too and not just a color and
some water you can do
the same thing blue or red or whatever
color you're using
and you can pull down
the color with let's do yellow green
but this pulling method is my favorite
way to show
a gradient between dark and light colors
um or between two different colors so
you can pull it
like so and it will gradually bleed
and you can help it bleed a little bit
more if it's not bleeding the way you
want it to
or how much you want it to then just go
back on that edge and kind of poke it
same thing over here if you want it to
bleed a little bit more
just kind of do that so pulling
pushing would be the next uh
way of using wet and wet it's
literally the same but opposite so we're
gonna push
two colors or a dark and a light color
into each other so let's say we have
this swatch area here maybe it's a petal
or a shape of some sort
and next i am going to push opera rose
into my prussian blue
create a slightly different experience
of these blends
but you want to make sure you just
barely touch the edge
so that it does the mixing for you
and again if you want it to blend a
little bit more we can just kind of
scoop that in there
[Music]
but these areas where you see some
shading or gradual blending those are
called blooms
so those blooms um depending on
if there's too much water like right
here is gonna dry
kind of weird so i'm gonna soak that up
there's too much water
that water is gonna act like a wall and
it's to block the
blending from happening so you want to
make sure that you're not using too much
water when you're
painting with wet and wet obviously we
need water for this magic moment to
happen
but just keep in mind that it's a
balance between
not enough water and too much water and
you always want to make sure you kind of
dab or soak up the excess water on your
paper towel or swipe it off on the edge
of your cup
so pulling pushing and then the next one
that i'm going to show you is poking
let's say i have a petal
or something that i'm painting that's a
really light blue
first and i want to add some
let's just do a circle shape i want to
add some
dots to it or darker color to it
this is where some really fun magic
happens maybe you're painting a night
sky
or you're painting a ocean
this is manganese blue and i'm just
going to poke it on
this area of wet either pigment or just
water
so you can do this to add texture or
ripples to
water it's a fun way to create water
effect
or to sit on a color and add
more on top of it
like so but it creates
a fun and the more you sit on the same
spot
the more it's going to burst open or the
bigger it's going to be
and right here i have some water kind of
pooling so this burst didn't happen as
big as these ones because
the water is too puddly it's acting like
a wall
so up here it's going to do more than
the areas that are puddles
so you can use poking for a spotted
effect on an animal
like maybe a cheetah obviously this is a
funky colored cheetah
moment um
good to use in water or to darken
certain colors
fun effects with
wet and wet painting
so practice these three
ways of wet and wet painting
and wet and dry is going to be exactly
how it sounds
you're going to add detail on top of it
so let's say this
is dry
and i want to add some detail
on top it's still a little wet so it
might not work but
you know maybe you're adding some petal
details or
if it's an abstract you're adding some
pattern on top of the wash
so this dark blue is the wet on top of
the light blue which is dry wet and dry
it's where you add details
so wet and wet is perfect for soft
gradients or soft blends between hues
and values
bursts of color blooms and then wet and
dry is for adding details
fine lines and crisp hard lines
so with watercolor there are two
different holds that i'm going to call
out or
handles so you can have a vertical hold
which means that your
brush is pointed more vertically up and
down
and a slanted hold a vertical hold can
get you
a wide stroke and a thin stroke but with
a round brush this is the reason why i
use
round brushes with a round brush your
brush is you know
a fine point so if you wanted to get a
really thin
branch or outline of a shape like a
circle
if you put little to no pressure on a
vertical hold with your brush you're
going to get a really thin
crisp line but if you do the same thing
vertical hold and apply pressure then
the hair of the brush is going to spread
out and you're going to get
you're going to fill in let's say a
circle a lot quicker and so we're going
to practice painting
circle totems like just columns of
circles
while we're also using wet and wet
technique um so don't stress out too
much this is just to get you to focus on
brush technique and going
between a vertical hold and a slanted
hold slanted holds i use slanted holds
most of the time to blend something
in or to soften wet and wet blending or
to color something in quicker than just
sitting there and coloring in the circle
with the tip of my brush because the
slanted hold
allows me to use the belly of the brush
vertical hold again we're going to be
using the tip of the brush the stroke is
going to look very different
than if we use a slanted hold the stroke
is going to look very different
too depending on what you're painting so
let's say i'm painting
i'm just going to grab a little practice
sheet here
this is going to be in a future video
with compound strokes but
the way you hold the brush is also going
to affect the way the stroke or the
subject whatever you're painting the
shape
looks so if let's say i'm painting a
leaf it's going to look a lot
differently
if i'm using a more vertical hold like
this with the tip
and then i'm putting pressure on it like
this than if i'm using
this the belly of the leaf so obviously
i'm using the same pressure and
technique
belly of the brush so obviously i'm
using the same technique i'm putting
pressure on my brush
and then releasing pressure but one i'm
using the tip of the brush the other one
i'm using
the belly of the brush pressure release
and it looks more
like a finger or just as more
of a sharp edge so the way you hold your
brush is going to be really important
with the overall shape of whatever
you're creating
so for this exercise i'm just going to
use my size 16 brush
and my 16 round brush and we're only
going to be painting circles
i'm going to start with you know a
darker color it can be anything that you
want it can be a lighter color too if
you want but i'm starting with prussian
blue
and a lot of it on my brush and to
create a circle
a smooth edge circle i'm going to use a
vertical hold so my brush is pretty much
straight up and down if you start to see
a little droplet forming make sure you
dab
your paper towel or swipe off that
excess water so it doesn't
create a big blop on your paper so i'm
going to use a vertical hold
and the way i'm holding the brush is
whatever is comfortable to me but i want
to get kind of
down on the ferrule or the handle of the
brush pretty far
and i'm just going to use my fingers to
swirl around
the edge of this circle and you can put
pressure on this brush or no pressure so
you get like a really fine line but the
less pressure you put on the brush the
more wobbly it's going to look
so i'm putting pressure on it as i swirl
it around
the circle and then i'm not going to sit
there with a vertical hold and color it
in
i'm going to use a slanted halt
to quickly color it in because we're
painting
wet and wet galaxies or totem whatever
you want to call this
and so my next circle i am going to
just use water you can use turquoise you
can use pink whatever you want to but
i'm just going to use water for
mine and i'm going to do the same thing
swirl around the outline of this circle
and then color it in quickly first but
now i want to show
how i would believe these two shapes
are using wet and wet so i'm going to
swirl
my brush gradually increase
the width or the circumference of this
circle
swirling around and then just barely
swipe
and we get some magic we're creating
like
snowmen next color let's
do a warm color i'm going to use opera
rose
you can stick with just cool colors this
is just practice
brush technique practice so we're not
really thinking about color theory and
composition and where it's landing and
all that kind of stuff we're just
practicing our brushes
maybe i'm gonna do a small pink circle
here
color it in with the belly of my brush
with the slanted hold
and then gradually increase the size
and touch
clean it up
maybe some orange for my next one
so practice bigger size circles and
smaller size circles so you can really
get used to how it feels we're doing the
same
vertical hold to start and then slanted
to color it in unless it's like tiny
tiny circle then
there's no need but practicing getting
really really smooth
and um
smooth outlines of your circle even
because the smaller you get the harder
it's going to be
so just be really delicate and patient
with it if you have a really shaky hand
you can put your free hand down like a
fist
and stabilize your painting hand on top
of it that really helps
just you know lay off the coffee maybe
while you're practicing your brush
techniques
so this is a super super simple painting
just circles outline with the vertical
hold
slanted hold to color it in but it's so
fun to look at
like just these lined up
galaxies or circles
so these smaller ones you can just color
in with your vertical hold
if you want something to blend a little
bit more you just gotta scoop
scoop it in just do a bright yellow next
[Music]
and maybe back to some pink
some manganese manganese blue
for a bright purple pink
yellow and purple are contrasting colors
we've got yellow green
and pink pinkish purple so we're not
still got some contrast but not crazy
fun stuff we can come over here and
create
more totems more practice
[Music]
outline with your vertical hold and
swirl
[Music]
slanted hold to color in
and then just gradually get
bigger
so it may seem redundant or boring but
this practice is very very valuable
in developing that muscle memory for
painting anything for painting flowers
for painting
portraits you name it the stroke
or brush technique is very very
important to practice
[Music]
do
one more over here
[Music]
fun fun it's like kind of like
moon phases but they're not moons
they're just colorful balls
[Music]
so figure out what hold feels best for
you if you like
you know holding it further away from
the tip of the brush or if you like
being really up close
when i'm swirling like this i kind of
like to get further away sometimes
because it
feels like i have better control it's
not
it's not as wobbly
but it may seem redundant and like we're
just doing a bunch of circles over and
over again but it's actually getting you
more and more comfortable with
how to hold the brush and how what types
of holes
slanted or vertical to use for certain
areas
whether you're coloring something in or
creating an outline
and different angles too are going to
get you more
or less coverage
and then also getting used to wet and
wet painting just a little bit more too
[Music]
you want to make sure you're focusing on
painting relatively quickly
if you're wanting to see these big
bursts and blooms
um because this is how wet and wet
painting works if
one of your circles is too dry and you
put a circle right next to it
to bleed it's not going to because it's
dry so you want to make sure
that you're working kind of quickly and
that's what's also going to get you
really comfortable with the brush too
if you're not over thinking things and
just kind of
going for it and getting used to how the
shapes form
with the two different style holds
like so and then you have a really fun
and colorful painting at the end of it
alrighty so now that we've covered
all things supplies if you're watching
this large video all together not pieced
out
we've colored covered supplies we've
colored
goodness we've covered supplies we've
covered color theory
we've covered wet and wet versus wet and
dry and we've also
covered brush techniques with our circle
piece and that has
gotten us comfortable with vertical
holds versus slanted holds
now we're going to combine over combine
our vertical and slanted whole together
in one foul swoop for using a compound
stroke so a compound stroke just means
we're going to be using a vertical
and a slanted hold along with that with
our vertical hold we're going to be
using
uh and slanted or slanted hold we're
going to be using pressure
and release of pressure so it's a
compound stroke because we're doing
multiple things
in one stroke without lifting our brush
and to practice this
we're going to be painting leaves so i'm
going to be using my size 6 brush
and um i'm gonna show you how to paint
some leaves individually by themselves
first
first and i'm gonna grab some water on
my brush
and sap green so you can see because
we're obviously painting leaves but
compound strokes don't just happen with
leaves this is just a good example
so to paint a leaf you want to point
your brush
handle the same direction the point
of the leaf is going to point so if my
leaf is going to point
this way but the handle of my brush is
going to be literally
pointing the same direction if my leaf
is going to point down at me
then i'm going to point my brush down at
me as well i'm not going to be using
the side of the brush to paint the leaf
that's going to look
very differently i'm going to be using
the tip of the brush
to flow through this compound stroke so
it'll make more sense once you start
practicing it
and just as a disclaimer before you
actually start painting leaves
leaves are tricky because they are
compound strokes
so this is something to always be
practicing and to do it over and over
again
is this compound stroke because this is
what's really going to make you very
comfortable with
with brushes and getting into that flow
state and just kind of painting
is practicing compound strokes so for my
leaf
i'm holding my brush at in between a
slanted and a vertical hold so i'm
right about 45 ish degree angle away
from my paper
and i'm gonna start with just a little
stem because a floating leaf looks a
little
weird but this is with little to no
pressure
i'm just adding a little stem that's not
a part of the compound stroke it's just
so the leaf doesn't look like a floating
taco
uh so i got a little stem and at 45
degrees
holding my brush at 45 degrees i am
going to at the top of this part
apply pressure and drag my brush in a
straight line
and as i do so i'm going to gradually
release that pressure
and get really really thin so
this is a very fine point with your
round brushes
and i'm going to finish this leaf but
then i'm going to show you what a lot of
beginners do when they're painting their
leaves is they don't get
thin enough at the end so we did
pressure
which the fanning of the brush is what
creates the width of the leaf and then
you gradually release that pressure so
it gets really really thin for the tip
of the leaf
so that's one side and then the other
side you're doing the same thing we're
starting at the same exact spot
we're just kind of curving down with
pressure
and gradually releasing at the same spot
like so so a lot of beginners when
they're first painting leaves will
go too quickly they'll apply pressure
and then just flick
and you get this weird texture at the
top
or they will be really intimidated it
can go very very slow so their pressure
pressure pressure
pressure and then they just kind of lift
it and it gives this like rounded
leaf which is cute but it's not what
we're going for so if you want
a compound stroke leaf you're going to
start with a thin stroke
this is not the compound stroke but this
is just the base of the leaf with the
little stem
45 degree angle with your brush making
sure your brush handle is pointing the
same direction your leaf is pointing
and just dragging your arm across in a
straight line with
pressure and gradually releasing that
pressure
to get thin so when i put pressure on my
brush my brush kind of
flips up into a straight up for a
vertical hold so pressure
and gradually release you're not
a lot of beginners will do this too
you're not curving your brush
like this because then you'd have to
color it in that's just a it's not a
not a compound stroke anymore because
you have to color it in
so so
45 degree angle hold away from the paper
pressure drag gradually release as
you're dragging
get as thin as you can
start at the same spot pressure drag
gradually release
let's do a few more so you can see it up
close and then we're going to
create a full branch
so 45 degree angle hold let's say i want
my leaf to point
up and down so my handle of my brush is
going to point
up wherever my leaf is going to point
[Music]
pressure gradually release
see how thin you can get
now let's do a leaf pointing straight
across this way
so instead of angling my brush this this
way or this way i'm angling
straight across pressure
gradually release see i'm going in a
straight line too i'm not curving up or
down
the pressure is making my leaf fat
release let's go this way
pressure release
if you're struggling with this stroke
maybe the leaf is over too soon or
you're working through it too quickly
you can also practice
longer leaves like tulip leaves so i'm
doing the same thin stroke whatever
direction the leaf is pointing
and then i'm just dragging it out for a
longer period of time
and maybe curving with it and gradually
releasing pressure
so that could be like a tulip leaf
but this compound stroke
i use in leaves all the time but if i
want to show
fold in
leaves i'll do pressure release pressure
again then release
but compound strokes are used all of the
time in brush
lettering so all your down strokes and
your letters
are gonna be pressure so they're wide
and then all your up strokes or across
strokes are gonna be thin
um you'll use this technique if you're
painting some petals
i'll use compound strokes so it's used
all the time
and it's such a great thing to practice
but i guarantee you if this is your
first time painting leaves like this
you're going to be frustrated and uh
maybe feel like giving up but please
don't
it takes a while takes some patience to
really get that muscle memory so do a
few rows of these leaves by themselves
and next i'm going to show you how to
combine these leaves on
a branch so i'm going to paint a few
different branches
and if i were painting a full floral
piece or maybe a wreath with just leaves
in it
this is kind of how i would create color
balance
and whatnot with my leaves all right so
now i'm going to show you how to combine
your leaves
on an actual branch
for your leaves so a few different
color ways but this is kind of my
approach so i'm going to do
for my stem i'm going to do some burnt
umber with a touch of mars black
in it for a smokier brown instead of
more of like a chocolatey brown and i'm
using my size 6 brush
for stems i'm going to use a vertical
hold you don't have to go straight up
and down i'm going to use like a
80-ish degree angle away from my paper
and i'm pivoting from my elbow so
my elbow is resting on the table
and i am using little to no pressure
on my stem
to create a c curve a lot of people do
s curves or they put pressure
put pressure on their c curve
for their branch and it looks like an
eyebrow or if you do an s curve it just
kind of looks like a worm
so i'm doing a c curve
for my stem and i'm going to make the
base of my stem just a little bit
thicker
and then we're going to go leaf by leaf
with adding
our secondary stems so i've got
still this brown color i'm just going to
pull out
c curves i'm not going to curve in
towards the stem because that's going to
make it look like a saguaro cactus
but i'm curving out from the stem and
i'm going to add
some darker smokier greens with
a touch of brown and sap green and maybe
a touch of mars black
for some of them some lighter leaves
i'm just going to whatever direction the
stem is pointing is the direction my
leaf should be pointing if i put a leaf
here it's going to look like someone
snapped it off so we want the stem to be
growing into our leaf so our handle of
our brush is pointing in line with that
and we're doing the same thing compound
stroke pressure
release pressure
release and as i'm going up this
main stem i'm going
leaf by leaf with my
secondary stems and kind of staggering
on either side
so maybe this next one i'm going to add
a little bit of blue to my mixture
making sure to point the handle of my
brush
in line with that stem
[Music]
so now i want to create balance with
this blue green color i don't want it to
be
green over here blue green over here so
i'm gonna
add a blue green leaf here but maybe
it's a lighter value so i'm going to
grab this pigment with my brush
and just rinse it off with some water
for a lighter value
pressure release
and i love when leaves with this loose
style painting
overlap and start to bleed into each
other like this
if you're noticing a little puddle on
your leaves just soak it up with a dry
brush or paper towel
because that's going to create a wonky
hard line
next i'm going to do some sap green and
yellow green i'm just staggering my
colors
and my values so that it's creating
balance
and it doesn't feel like it's tipping in
one direction or another it's just
creating depth and balance because some
leaves are going to be overlapped some
leaves are going to be hitting
light and others will be more shaded
you can even add
leaves that are gonna overlap
let's do more of that blue-green since
it's on the left
just pull it over here a little bit more
darker blue green
overlap
maybe just sap green by itself for this
one
[Music]
and it's kind of overlapping that middle
stem
[Music]
so with every leaf i'm switching up the
hue slightly
creating balance across the whole stem
with hue and value
and let's do some more yellow green
and practicing these leaves on a single
stem over and over like this
is developing that muscle memory so even
if it's looking wonky to you
just keep doing it until you finish the
whole stem because you're practicing
muscle memory
with this compound stroke and it's not
easy
another thing that i want to mention too
with stems when you're doing a full stem
like this is a lot of people will bring
their
secondary stems really long and their
leaf will be
way over here and that's going to create
a big gap between your main stem and
your
secondary stem and it's just going to
feel really empty and weird so i'm going
really close
to the main stem
i'm only going like a quarter of an inch
out and i can always add more leaves
in between some of these if i want to if
their gap is feeling a little too
spaced out but going between a mixture
of sap green
prussian blue mars black and burnt umber
or sap green and yellow lemon yellow
deep
and mixing up values
i'm going to add in some more leaves
that are lighter
kind of poking through maybe here
and here
[Music]
so lighter value leaves but making sure
i'm dabbing
the excess water off on my paper towel
so i'm not using too much water that
will make a puddle
[Music]
so
so everything i've covered in this
watercolor basics video so far we're
combining
for this big stem with all these leaves
so compound strokes wet and wet painting
we've got some blending happening
between the stem and the leaves
and neighboring leaves um
we could go back on top of these leaves
once they dry and add
vein details if we wanted to using wet
and dry
we're using vertical and slanted holds
all of the things so these are great
leaves are a great thing to be
practicing over and over again
because you practice so much
pressure release
maybe half a leaf poking up here
like so
okay so now we're gonna paint a basic
flower combining
everything i've taught you so far about
compound strokes
with painting leaves vertical and
slanted holds
and we're gonna paint a basic flower i'm
gonna use a size six
brush you can grab just opera rose or
opera rose and scarlet like whatever
color you want your flower to be
and we're going to use a compound stroke
but instead of painting
a stroke like a leaf we are going to use
a slanted hold about 45 degrees away
from the paper
and apply pressure and then
as we curve around we're going to
release
pressure for this little
teardrop so we've got an upside down
teardrop so i'm going to do it again
so thin pressure
curve around and gradually release that
pressure
and then to make it look more like a
flower
you can do another smaller
same stroke like this
and maybe just have little petals that
are tucked
behind so this is our main petal and
then we've got another
bigger petal over here but all of
our teardrops or our all of our petals
are pointing
to create a v shape so we're not doing
our first teardrop
and then our second teardrop is
pointing down like this
because then the stem would be here and
that just doesn't make sense
so you want to make sure
you've got your first teardrop pressure
gradually release
and then you're pointing directly to
that same spot
pressure loop release
and then i just do pressure and kind of
curve in
then from here i'm just going to add a
stem
maybe some yellow green with sap green
and lemon yellow deep
in whatever direction this v is pointing
that's where my stem is going to be so
i'm going to
use little to no pressure on a vertical
hold with my brush
you can connect it or not connect it
and then we can add some leaves
using compound strokes that i showed you
in the previous video
or chapter
[Music]
so this is just a basic side view
of a flower maybe it's a tulip
but same thing that we were practicing
with our wet and wet technique and
the leaves when you're painting a full
floral piece you don't want
every single petal of every single
flower to be the same
hue and value so maybe some are more
pink than others
some are lighter
but i've got just three compound strokes
well two compound strokes in one little
c curve situation
and just
pressure and loop back down
and that white space between your petals
is what's going to make it look like a
flower because
your petals are separated by that white
space but you also don't want
your petals to be too far apart where
you have
petal here and
over here is your next petal and then
over here is your other petal
because then that looks too spaced out
and weird
so you want them to be touching but have
little slivers of white space
little little little slivers of white
space
so that it looks like separate petals
then if you want to do a basic open
flower we're going to use
a very different hold on your brush
we're going to use a slanted hold
but instead of using the going in line
with the handle of my brush
i'm going to go perpendicular to the
handle of my brush so instead of
bringing my stroke this way which is in
line with the handle same direction as
the handle of my brush
i'm going to go this way which is
perpendicular so
i'm gonna paint a basic open flower
with just these kind of up and down
wavy motions of my brush making sure
every petal is pointing back to the same
middle
this could be a cherry blossom
it could be
an anemone it
could be a pansy
let's do a pansy with just
three petals in like a triad
so i'm using the belly of the brush for
this simple stroke
and then for the pansy i'm going to go
back in and
use wet and wet painting
maybe up here too
and for your anemone you could go back
in with
black
or brown or yellow anemones will have
you want to make sure your petals are
dry these aren't but
we're just gonna be a little careful
so with people painting flowers
the biggest mistake i see is people
unaware of
how petals are connected together
so you want to think about how a flower
grows
and
each petal is connected to the same
center of the flower which is connected
to
the stem and so you want to make sure
that all of your petals are
are pointing at the same center point
so if we had
this petal just slightly shifted up like
this
pointing up that way that would not look
appropriate it would look really weird
because it's not connected to the same
center point so you want to make sure
that as you're going around with these
open shaped flowers
all your petals are pointing in towards
that same exact spot
so that it makes sense and then same
thing with your side facing
flower you want to create that v that v
shape like that v
shape because all of your petals are
going to be connected
if you think about like an orange for
example if you're peeling an orange from
the top
to bottom but you're leaving the peels
connected to the bottom they're all
connected to that bottom of the orange
it's the same thing with petals as a
petal
or as a flower opens that those petals
are still connected to the base so if
i'm looking at
the side view of a flower i'm seeing a v
shape but if i'm looking at the top of a
flower
i'm seeing a circle like so
so combining everything i've taught so
far in this watercolor basics series for
a floral wreath with flowers
compound strokes with our leaves wet and
wet technique
shapes curves all of the things
so i'm going to use my size 6 brush for
this wreath
and you can pencil out a circle
very very lightly for following a
specific shape if you want to i'm going
to freehand it and hope it works out
but it's just all about doing pieces of
branches
and seeing how the shape is forming so
that you're eyeballing it as you go
all right so first i'm going to start
with
the right side of my wreath kind of just
eyeballing
where i want to start it kind of in the
middle and coming over here
to the right side and i'm going to do
my slanted-ish hold or vertical
it's like in between hold and
c-curve for
my first little branch that i'm going to
add leaves to
and if you're like whoa that's going to
be a tiny circle don't you worry i'm
going to start piecing over here
so even if you curve a little too far in
or two over here
you can just add branches to fill it in
and design the curve
so let's do some compound strokes i'm
gonna do
some blue green for leaves maybe a touch
of
burnt umber and we're going to start
really dark
then get a little bit lighter
[Music]
and right here is an open space where i
can either
add a flower or another leaf
what i want to make sure of as i'm going
around this whole leaf though
or bran what is this this whole wreath
is that i have balance so i've mentioned
this before in this series but balance
is really important in composition if
something feels like it's tipping toward
one side of the or the other it's gonna
feel off to your viewers so i want to
make sure to incorporate flowers
along my entire wreath so that it feels
balanced and not like it's tipping too
heavy
on this side with flowers and there's
nothing down here so i'm going to paint
in a little flower maybe
part of a pansy an open-faced pandy i'm
going to start with some
cobalt maybe a touch of opera rose
lightly
and i'm using the side or belly of my
brush
to give it these
little pokes here
and then using wet and wet painting to
give it
that darker color bleed
and we got a pansy going
and maybe another pansy but it's more
purple
or has more pink in the cobalt mixture
just
right here
[Music]
so obviously i'm not sketching anything
before
um this is just allowing me to practice
freehand
and
just going for it i'm focusing on
balance and i'm focusing on
shape and you get there by developing
muscle memory for all
of these elements so all of the florals
branches and leaves if you're not
comfortable with them
individually it's going to be really
hard for you to freehand something like
this
but i'm using the curves of leaves
to help guide my the shape of my wreath
and noticing areas where i want some
bursts of color
purple and yellow are contrasting colors
so i'm incorporating some
contrast down here i want to make sure
to incorporate that throughout the
wreath and not just have it right there
so keeping that in mind for future
and working my way up with another stem
pressure release pressure release
[Music]
so making sure to not just have the same
hue and value
of all my leaves and flowers and
whatever elements i'm painting
because as you can see i've got blue
green fading to yellow green and there's
lighter values in between that's going
to create a lot more movement than just
using secondary green in the same value
for every single leaf
so it's going to create a lot more
movement and fullness
now i'm going to so i've got some with
my floral elements i've got some purples
and blues
happening i want to get a little bit
more like a rainbow vibe with all my
colors so
i'm gonna add some indigo or turquoisey
color with manganese blue
and a touch of prussian blue
and maybe just do side facing
flower here
and here
and a lemon yellow or a yellow green
stem for these
kind of not berries but just little buds
of flowers
i'm just tapering off here and following
my
my circle ish adding in little leaves to
frame
okay we've got a nice curve let's start
to curve
across
and get into some more yellow orange and
red
pinky colors for our florals
eventually
[Music]
so this shape i want it to curve down
a little bit more
[Music]
pressure release
nice open area here for a fuller flower
more open flower
maybe we do some yellow
maybe take opera rose and cadmium orange
to
add the center bleed
copper rose and lemon yellow deep for my
side facing flower over here
and get gradually more pink
[Music]
and curving with adding stems and leaves
and as i'm starting to curve around here
i want to see how it's filling out if
it's feeling too boxy then i'll
add little leaves here and there
we've got a really dark leaf right there
so i want to make sure it doesn't feel
too heavy or unbalanced so i'm going to
bring
a darker blue green leaf here
and bring in some more brown
using all the colors
yep got some water droplets we're gonna
cover up with some leaves
boom
[Music]
light values dark values
looking as you're painting for
shapes balance
where it feels like it's tipping or
maybe feels too heavy
[Music]
or not dense enough
and i'll just get some more reds
pinks and then a little more purple here
to close it off
[Music]
off a rose man it's so bright
a pinkish pansy open right here
[Music]
so with pink it's
basically like red uh on the color wheel
instead of adding secondary green so
just sap green next to it for my leaves
i'm gonna
shift the hue a little bit more and add
more yellow to the mixture
this yellow green is really going to pop
next to it
because green and pink are contrasting
colors but
we're not using the direct contrast with
yellow green
i'm going to add some yellow up here
it's going to get tons of yellow it kind
of became orange pretty quickly so we're
going to just
do these little side facing yellows here
poking out because it's also a little
bit of a straight line from this leaf to
that leaf so it's
not curved enough or bumpy enough
a little poke in here
[Music]
little fluffs
and a bit more orange up here
these side facing flowers are so easy to
just add in these tight
tight spots where it just needs a little
bit more balance
we've got a small cluster of turquoise
here but everything's out a little bit
more spread out so i'm going to
bring it down here too
so always thinking about balance in
individual sections of
whatever type of piece you're painting
whether it's a wreath or a full
floral piece thinking about balance how
it's tipping
incorporating movement with value scales
within one
section and hue scales
all things that we've covered in the
series
but pulling together for one big piece
[Music]
now let's get a little purple so we can
finish it off for a rainbow
wreath just getting gradually more and
more purple by adding prussian blue to
this
opera rose prussian blue mixture
with these
side facing flowers tulips whatever they
are
[Music]
brown stems because it's a lot of green
stems over here
making sure my stem is pointing in line
with the v
of the flower
and maybe finish it off with some leaves
it's getting flat right here so we're
going to want to come
out a little bit more to make it heavier
down here
and incorporate that dark blue green so
i'm going to make this a little darker
so i'm able to paint this a bit quicker
because i am so comfortable with
how these strokes are formed compound
strokes
color theory color balance
all of that kind of stuff that
it takes practice and
doing it something over and over again
to really
understand how to incorporate it in a
bigger piece like this
and make it feel balanced
but any area where i feel like something
is really standing out or
calling too much attention i know it's
either
a shape imbalance or it needs
some color depth like
with values and
hue variation
just keeping that in mind we're getting
heavy down here so we need to thicken
this area out
[Music]
so
knowing when when to stop is also a good
thing too
so we don't want to get too crazy with
all these fluffs
around our leaves but just looking at
how it's forming areas that feel a
little
like this kind kind of comes to a point
up here whereas this is kind of all
starting to
make a circle so i'm gonna add some
yellow here
something that i always find
interesting about some comments that we
get or
messages i receive on instagram from
people who are just starting out or
maybe i've never painted like this
before but they've been painting for a
while
is that there's a lot of
people out there and i totally get why
but there's a lot of people out there
that
are trying to hurry the process and be
further along than
they should be and
maybe it's part of our culture or with
social media and being able to see all
of the
brilliant work out there and getting
discouraged with wherever you're at in
your process but
i think the most important part is
of getting better over time is being
okay with where you're at
and that like mental
mental muscle that you have to flex
in order to not get bothered or
frustrated
or overwhelmed when something isn't
turning out the way
teachers is or the way you think it
should um
but not letting that overwhelm or that
like
discouragement get the best of you
because a lot of people give up
when something doesn't turn out the way
they want to but they don't realize that
every artist has
crumpled up paper in their trash can so
keep that in mind and then with our
final details we're going to use wet and
wet painting
to add
little stamen areas to like this
lemon yellow deep here to this pansy
[Music]
just tiny little details
you can use gouache which is a version
of watercolor
it's just more opaque if you want for
this for it to stand out a little more
but i'm just gonna use watercolor
now i hope that video was helpful for
you if you need further
resources and research please check out
that free ebook i mentioned
i have a floral watercolor ebook that
goes over all the things that i covered
in this
series which i cover brush techniques
supplies color theory everything so if
you need a guide
to walk you through step by step as
you're watching these videos make sure
you go download that freebie
and then also check out my book everyday
watercolor if you want a bit more
in-depth
color theory and also basic shapes
compound
strokes all of the things and more in my
book everyday watercolor
which is an amazon and also available in
local bookstores so make sure you check
that out as well
and we just recently launched a patreon
channel where i'm going way more in
depth with patrons who are spending five
dollars a month and
up with us where we've got a patreon
only exclusive tutorial every single
month going out for five dollars a month
and up tiers
along with a live monthly art class
where you can sit with me ask me
questions while i'm painting
and teaching um while i'm going through
things live if you spend ten dollars a
month and
up through our tier so make sure you
check out our patreon my everyday
watercolor books
my freebie also i have a way more
in-depth watercolor course in the works
we'll link it below in the description
right now if you want to join the wait
list if
if it isn't open click that link and you
can find out more information on that
also just remember if you want quick
reference for any of the chapters in
this video we segmented every single one
of them out and they are available in my
watercolor basics playlist make sure you
go check that out we'll link to that
here so you can check it out and i'll
see you in the next video
you